# **BILAL KASSIM**

bilalabdulkassim@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/bilal-kassim/

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Electrical and electronics engineering graduate with more than one year of experience in embedded systems seeking an opportunity to enter into an esteemed organization, to carve out a niche for myself and emerge as a good Professional to mark my excellence while actively contributing to the development of the organization employing my skills

### **EDUCATION**

# APJ Abdul Kalam Technological University, India Bachelor of Technology in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

07/2017-07/2021

- CGPA 7.11/10
- Core Modules: Power Generation Transmission & Protection, Power System Analysis, Distributed Generation & Smart-grids, Industrial Instrumentation & Automation, Electrical System Design, Special Electric Machines, Power Electronics, DC Machines & Transformers, Synchronous & Induction Machines
- Completed additional coursework in Biomedical Instrumentation, Electric and Hybrid Vehicles, Internet of Things, and Sensors & Actuators
- Co-authored a research paper related to multi-purpose unmanned aerial vehicle for different harsh applications and published it in International Journal of Advanced Research in Electrical, Electronics, and Instrumentation Engineering (IJAREEIE), Volume 10, Issue 6, June 2021

# Kerala State Board of Higher Secondary Education

05/2014-05/2016

• Percentage 88.7/100

## WORK EXPERIENCE

# **Tata Consultancy Services – General Motors**

12/2021 - Present

## Job title: Assistant System Engineer

- Responsible for development, integration, behavioural testing of automotive embedded software accord with AUTOSAR architecture
- Requirement analysis using IBM DOORS
- Worked with MATLAB/Simulink for the development and simulation of the Body Control Module
- Software integration of the Body Control Module ECU and releasing its artifacts to General Motors and flashing the software into the microcontroller
- Key behavioural testing, hand fixes, debugging with Vehicle Spy, GHS Multi
- Exposure to software development life cycle: V model, Agile
- Experience working with IBM Rhapsody, Jenkins, Git Ecosystem, Jira
- Experience in communication protocols like CAN, LIN, I2C
- Experience with ARM Cortex microcontrollers
- Hands on experience in Embedded C, MATLAB scripting
- Documentation and analytic briefing using MS Office and presenting it to fellow engineers, leads, project managers

# Kerala State Electricity Board Ltd, Kerala, India

06/2019 - 07/2019

# Trainee Engineer (Internship)

· Worked in 110 KV Substation as a trainee engineer

- Achieved industrial exposure to designing and analysing electrical system layout, load analysis of different feeders, switching of feeders and tapping of transformers
- Analysed and understood solar energy's importance in consumer-level energy management

### **PROJECTS**

- Multi-Purpose Unmanned Aerial Vehicle: Project revolves around drones which helps in automatic
  high altitude painting improving safety and reducing the time of painting workers, to reduce smog in the
  environment
- **Home Automation**: Control different equipment like fans, lights, agricultural irrigation system automatically using embedded systems

### ADDITIONAL COURSES TAKEN

- Crash Course on Python: An online course authorised by University of Buffalo and The State University of New York offered through Coursera
- Python Quick Start: LinkedIn
- Certificate course on C programming: Course conducted by G-tec Computer Education
- Specialization in Internet of Things and Embedded systems: An online course authorised by University of California; Irvine offered through Coursera
- MATLAB Onramp: MathWorks Training Services
- Machine Learning Onramp: MathWorks Training Services
- Learning Java: LinkedIn

### SKILLS AND INTEREST

Technical Skills : MATLAB/Simulink, Electrical system design, MS Office, C, Python

• Languages : English (Fluent), Hindi (Fluent), Malayalam (Native), Arabic (Basics), German

(Basics)

Personal Skills : Multitasking, Effective Intelligence, Organizing Ability, Sense of

Responsibility, Social adaptability and Quick Learner

• Interest : Travelling, Football, Cooking and Driving

# EXTRA CURRICULAR

- Logistics Head in national level inter-college technical fest called **TAKSHAK'19**, prepared budget, provided electrical and sound systems and supervised delegation of responsibilities
- Represented school in Kerala state level school athletics meet
- SPARSHAM: Organised mini marathon for disabled peoples under national level inter-college art fest called SANSKRITI'20

## **VOLUNTEERING**

- Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (**IEEE**) active member
- National Service Scheme (NSS): As an active member provides an opportunity to work for the social welfare of students and served 2018 flood affected regions of Kerala
- National Cadet Corps (NCC)